<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>NLP | Shaojie Jiang&#39;s Homepage</title>
    <link>https://example.com/category/nlp/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://example.com/category/nlp/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>NLP</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 16 May 2020 16:40:07 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://example.com/media/icon_hubc11b102ed638ad8eb587d60e1601a1f_37041_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>NLP</title>
      <link>https://example.com/category/nlp/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Transformer Align Model</title>
      <link>https://example.com/post/en/transformer-align-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 May 2020 16:40:07 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/post/en/transformer-align-model/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this paper&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, transformer is trained to perform both translation and alignment tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;application-scenarios-of-word-alignments-in-nmt&#34;&gt;Application scenarios of word alignments in NMT&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Generating bilingual lexica from parallel corpora&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;External dictionary assisted translation to improve translation of low frequency words&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trust, explanation, error analysis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Preserving style on webpages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;model-design&#34;&gt;Model design&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The attention mechanism has long been motivated by word alignments in statistical machine translation, but ensure the alignment quality, additional supervision is needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a tendency that the attention probabilities from the penultimate layer of a normally trained transformer MT model corresponds to word alignments.
Therefore, one attention head (clever!) in the penultimate layer is trained as the alignment head.
The motivation of selecting only one attention head for alignment is to give the freedom to the model of choosing whether to rely more on the alignment or other attention heads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- While in Beamer alignment, the freedom is fully preserved in the attention layer, and the alignment is used for RNN hidden states. --&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-two-train-the-alignment-head&#34;&gt;How two train the alignment head&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two approaches existing in the literature:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Label alignments beforehand and train the attention weights through KL-divergence.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use the attentional vector to also predict either the target word or the properties such as POS tags of the target tokens.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this work, an unsupervised training approach is used to train the alignment head.
An alignment model is first trained on translation, then the penultimate layer attention weights are averaged and used as weak alignment supervision for a translation (and alignment) model.
The alignment model is trained in both directions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Previous work reported performance gain by introducing alignment supervision.
In this paper, however, alignment performances are good, but translation results are moderate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1909.02074&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Jointly Learning to Align and Translate with Transformer Models&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Compressive Transformers</title>
      <link>https://example.com/post/en/compressive-transformers/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 May 2020 14:29:44 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/post/en/compressive-transformers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Built on top of Transformer-XL, Compressive Transformer&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; condenses old memories (hidden states) and stores them in the compressed memory buffer, before completely discarding them.
This model is suitable for long-range sequence learning but may cause too much computational burden for tasks that only have short sequences.
Compressive Transformers can also be used as memory components in conjunction with other models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the beginning, the authors draw the connection between their work and human brains by mentioning that humans memorize things via lossy compression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We aggressively select, filter, or integrate input stimuli based on factors of surprise, perceived danger, or repetition &amp;ndash; amongst other signals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s often, if not always, good to see such insights of how AI works are inspired by humans.
It&amp;rsquo;s also good to see that they relate their work to previous works, i.e. RNNs, transformers and sparse attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An RNN compresses previous memories into a fixed size hidden vector, which is space-efficient, but also results in its temporal nature and hence difficult to parallelize.
Transformers, on the other hand, store all the past memories uncompressed, which can be beneficial for achieving better performances such as precision, BLEU, perplexity, etc, but it costs more and more computation and memory space with the sequence length growing.
Sparse attention can be used to reduce computation, while the spatial cost remains the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;model-design-and-training&#34;&gt;Model design and training&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The proposed Compressive Transformer uses the same attention mechanism over its set of memories and compressed memories, trained to query both its short-term granular memory and longer-term coarse memory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If trained using original task-relevant loss only, it requires backpropagating-through-time (BPTT) over long unrolls for very old memories.
A better solution is to use local auxiliary losses by stopping gradients and reconstructing either the original memory vectors (lossless objective) or attention vectors (lossy objective; reportedly to work better).
The second choice for the auxiliary loss, in other words, means that we don&amp;rsquo;t care whether the original memory can be reconstructed or not, as long as the attention vector can be reconstructed, given the same query (brilliant!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;some-practical-concerns&#34;&gt;Some practical concerns&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The auxiliary loss is only used to train the compression module, as it harms the learning when the gradients flow back to the main network.
This might also explain why I couldn&amp;rsquo;t reproduce &lt;a href=&#34;../adaptive-computation-time&#34;&gt;ACT&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Batch accumulation (4x bigger batch size) is used for better performance.
It is observed in some works that bigger batch sizes lead to better generalization, but some other works found the opposite to be true (discussed in the papers and talks mentioned &lt;a href=&#34;../visualizing-loss&#34;&gt;in my other post&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Model optimization is very sensitive to gradient scales, so the gradient norms are clipped to 0.1 for stable results.
This is typical for transformer variants.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Convolution works best for memory compression.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;further-thoughsquestions&#34;&gt;Further thoughs/questions:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compressive Transformer improves the modeling of rare words.
But why?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the discussion section, the authors pointed out that future directions could include the investigation of adaptive compression rates by layer, the use of long-range shallow memory layers together with deep short-range memory, and even the use of RNNs as compressors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;section class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1911.05507&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Compressive Transformers for Long-Range Sequence Modelling&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What&#39;s New in XLNet?</title>
      <link>https://example.com/post/en/xlnet/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/post/en/xlnet/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;rip-bert&#34;&gt;R.I.P BERT&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1810.04805&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;BERT&lt;/a&gt; got a head shot yesterday, by another guy called &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1906.08237&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;XLNet&lt;/a&gt;.
It is reported that XLNet defeated BERT on 20 NLP tasks, and achieved 18 new state-of-the-art results.
Isn&amp;rsquo;t it impressive?
So, farewell, BERT.














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-rip-bert&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;R.I.P BERT&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/en/xlnet/images/bert_dead_hu61e83ca8534a90d5b1ebee93953bac39_29320_6857e2260ab446b51f13608b386eff69.jpg 400w,
               /post/en/xlnet/images/bert_dead_hu61e83ca8534a90d5b1ebee93953bac39_29320_526b97597aa9149c17bad8b30b8af9af.jpg 760w,
               /post/en/xlnet/images/bert_dead_hu61e83ca8534a90d5b1ebee93953bac39_29320_1200x1200_fit_q75_lanczos.jpg 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/post/en/xlnet/images/bert_dead_hu61e83ca8534a90d5b1ebee93953bac39_29320_6857e2260ab446b51f13608b386eff69.jpg&#34;
               width=&#34;570&#34;
               height=&#34;570&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      R.I.P BERT
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;is-bert-really-dead&#34;&gt;Is BERT really dead?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I love BERT, I decided to read the paper to find out what killed him.
While reading, I was thinking wait a minute, is BERT really dead?
After finished the paper, I was so glad to know that BERT is still well alive!
He is just wearing another coat named &lt;em&gt;Two-Stream Self-Attention (TSSA)&lt;/em&gt;, with some other gadgets!
Because:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;code&gt;XLNet = BERT + TSSA + bidirectional data input&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Bert you&amp;rsquo;re so tough, buddy!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s take a closer look at what were trying to kill BERT.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;two-stream-self-attention-tssa&#34;&gt;Two-stream self-attention (TSSA)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why TSSA is needed to kill BERT?
Well, let&amp;rsquo;s first see some weaknesses BERT has.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BERT is using a masked language model (MLM) training objective, which is essentially why it achieves bidirectional representation.














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-image-sourcehttpsnlpstanfordeduseminardetailsjdevlinpdf&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;[Image source](https://nlp.stanford.edu/seminar/details/jdevlin.pdf)&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/en/xlnet/images/MLM_hub4c01273cdd2a52becfd097515ece19b_34267_6ac9179d307010de4dbb4ffedc7ed2bd.png 400w,
               /post/en/xlnet/images/MLM_hub4c01273cdd2a52becfd097515ece19b_34267_8558609a8e5d6f3d0d698c4c338b2d61.png 760w,
               /post/en/xlnet/images/MLM_hub4c01273cdd2a52becfd097515ece19b_34267_1200x1200_fit_lanczos_3.png 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/post/en/xlnet/images/MLM_hub4c01273cdd2a52becfd097515ece19b_34267_6ac9179d307010de4dbb4ffedc7ed2bd.png&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;103&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;a href=&#34;https://nlp.stanford.edu/seminar/details/jdevlin.pdf&#34;&gt;Image source&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this example, both words &amp;ldquo;store&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;gallon&amp;rdquo; are intended to be predicted by BERT, and their input word embeddings are replaced by the embedding of a special token &lt;em&gt;[MASK]&lt;/em&gt;.
Usually this isn&amp;rsquo;t a problem, but what if the prediction of &amp;ldquo;store&amp;rdquo; requires knowing the word &amp;ldquo;gallon&amp;rdquo;?
That is exactly where BERT falls short.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TSSA is what you can use to overcome that downside of MLM:














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-query-stream-sourcehttpsarxivorgabs190608237&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Query stream, [source](https://arxiv.org/abs/1906.08237)&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/en/xlnet/images/query_stream_hued03336a8aeea8af3524f5a71c4c5e85_138678_38dac758cb839cc6972fe3fb4a965216.png 400w,
               /post/en/xlnet/images/query_stream_hued03336a8aeea8af3524f5a71c4c5e85_138678_98626a8d08caed422203da248c1ca4cc.png 760w,
               /post/en/xlnet/images/query_stream_hued03336a8aeea8af3524f5a71c4c5e85_138678_1200x1200_fit_lanczos_3.png 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/post/en/xlnet/images/query_stream_hued03336a8aeea8af3524f5a71c4c5e85_138678_38dac758cb839cc6972fe3fb4a965216.png&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;645&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Query stream, &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1906.08237&#34;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this illustration, query stream gives you the &lt;code&gt;query&lt;/code&gt; vector needed for attention calculation, and this stream is designed in such a way that it doesn&amp;rsquo;t leak the info of the word it&amp;rsquo;s going to predict, but guarantees all information from other positions.
Take $x_1$ for example: $x_1$&amp;rsquo;s embedding (and hidden state) is not used at all, but embeddings and hidden states from other positions are used in each layer.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-content-stream-sourcehttpsarxivorgabs190608237&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Content stream, [source](https://arxiv.org/abs/1906.08237)&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/en/xlnet/images/content_stream_hude0ab6174270e4e71fb20a58d5784b5d_120246_35ebc2272312cf14f7535059af84f6b6.png 400w,
               /post/en/xlnet/images/content_stream_hude0ab6174270e4e71fb20a58d5784b5d_120246_aad57049ce431e4543450b2ad7b1b34c.png 760w,
               /post/en/xlnet/images/content_stream_hude0ab6174270e4e71fb20a58d5784b5d_120246_1200x1200_fit_lanczos_3.png 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/post/en/xlnet/images/content_stream_hude0ab6174270e4e71fb20a58d5784b5d_120246_35ebc2272312cf14f7535059af84f6b6.png&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;561&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Content stream, &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1906.08237&#34;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Content stream, on the other hand, gives you the &lt;code&gt;key&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;value&lt;/code&gt; vectors needed for context vector calculation.
This stream uses a strategy similar to that in a standard &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/pdf/1706.03762.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Transformer decoder&lt;/a&gt; by masking future positions.
The only difference is that in content stream, the order of tokens is &lt;em&gt;randomly permuted&lt;/em&gt;.
For example $x_2$ is right after $x_3$, and therefore $h_2^{(1)}$ can only see the embedding of itself and that of $x_3$ (and $mem^{(0)}$), but not that of $x_1$ or $x_4$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;mask-a-span&#34;&gt;Mask a span&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another difference from BERT is masking a span of consecutive words.
The reason I guess, is that this guarantees the dependence of masked words (as claimed to be what BERT can&amp;rsquo;t model).
This is not a fresh-new idea, though.
Recently there are two ERNIE papers (BERT based) that propose masking named entities (often of multiple words, &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/pdf/1905.07129.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;paper link&lt;/a&gt;) and/or phrases (&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/pdf/1904.09223.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;paper link&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;bidirectional-data-input&#34;&gt;Bidirectional data input&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another notably different thing in XLNet is the usage of bidirectional data input.
The idea (I guess) is to decide the factorization direction (either forward or backward), so that the idea of &amp;ldquo;masking future positions&amp;rdquo; used in a standard Transformer decoder can also be easily used together with XLNet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Masking a span makes XLNet look like a denoising autoencoder; but by using bidirectional data input (or masking future positions), XLNet performs more like a autoregressive language model in the masked region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;closing-remarks&#34;&gt;Closing remarks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So now you probably can see the similarities and differences between XLNet and BERT.
If not, here is a quick summary:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Instead of masking random words, mask a span of words&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use bidirectional data input to decide which direction you treat as &amp;ldquo;future&amp;rdquo;, and then apply the idea of masking future positions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To avoid leaking the information of the position to be predicted, use Two-Stream Self-Attention (TSSA)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Other minor things like segment recurrence, relative positional encoding, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem to be enough changes to make all those improvements.
What if BERT is also trained using the additional data (Giga5, ClueWeb, Common Crawl), will XLNet still be able to defeat BERT?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EDIT:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Another model named &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1905.02450&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;MASS&lt;/a&gt; employs a very similar idea.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;According to Jacob Devlin (author of BERT), relative positional embedding might be of great importance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
