<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>paper reading notes | Shaojie Jiang</title>
    <link>https://shaojiejiang.github.io/category/paper-reading-notes/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://shaojiejiang.github.io/category/paper-reading-notes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>paper reading notes</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2020 Shaojie Jiang</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 06 May 2020 10:13:43 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://shaojiejiang.github.io/images/icon_hubc11b102ed638ad8eb587d60e1601a1f_37041_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>paper reading notes</title>
      <link>https://shaojiejiang.github.io/category/paper-reading-notes/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Visualizing the Loss Landscape of Neural Nets</title>
      <link>https://shaojiejiang.github.io/post/en/visualizing-loss/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 May 2020 10:13:43 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shaojiejiang.github.io/post/en/visualizing-loss/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here are some notes take while reading the NeurlIPS 2018 paper 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://papers.nips.cc/paper/7875-visualizing-the-loss-landscape-of-neural-nets&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Visualizing the Loss Landscape of Neural Nets&lt;/a&gt;.
This work helps explain why some models are easier to train/generalize than others.
The next question is how to get better models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The traditional way of visualizing loss functions of neural models in 2D contour plots is by choosing a center point $\theta^*$ (normally the converged model parameters), two random direction vectors $\delta$ and $\eta$, then plot the function:
$$f(\alpha, \beta) = L(\theta^* + \alpha \delta + \beta \eta)$$
Batch norm parameters are unchanged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above method fails to capture the intrinsic geometry of loss surfaces, and cannot be used to compare the geometry of two different minimizers or two different networks.
This is because of the &lt;em&gt;scale invariance&lt;/em&gt; in network weights (this statement only applies to rectified networks as per the paper).
To tackle this, the authors normalize each filter in a direction vector $d$ ($\delta$ or $\eta$) to have the same norm of the corresponding filter in $\theta$:
$$d_{i, j} \leftarrow \frac{d_{i, j}}{||d_{i, j}||} ||\theta_{i, j} ||.$$
$i$ is the layer number and $j$ the filter number.
With the proposed filter-wise normalized direction vectors, the authors found that the sharpness of local minima correlates well with generalization error, even better than layer-wise normalization (for direction vectors).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why flat minima:&lt;/strong&gt; In a recent talk&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, Tom Goldstein (the last author) pointed out that flat minima correspond to large margin classifiers, which is more tolerant to domain shifts of data, thus having better generalization ability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Known influential factors:&lt;/strong&gt;
Small-batch training results in flat minima, while large-batch training results in sharp minima.
Increased width prevents chaotic behavior, and skip connections dramatically widen minimizers (see figure in the beginning).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Interpreting with precaution:&lt;/strong&gt;
The loss surface is viewed under a dramatic dimensionality reduction.
According to the authors&amp;rsquo; analysis, if non-convexity is present in the dimensionality reduced plot, then non-convexity must be present in the full-dimensional surface as well.
However, apparent convexity in the low-dimensional surface does not mean the high-dimensional function is truly convex. Rather it means that the positive curvatures are dominant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further thoughts/questions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Has it been done for visualizing NLP models?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is it more appropriate to visualize loss for NLG or other measures?
This might depend on how to define &amp;ldquo;labels&amp;rdquo; in NLG tasks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How big a convolution filter normally is?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s similar between RNN and skip connections?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;section class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://iclr2020deepdiffeq.rice.edu/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Generalization in neural nets:  a perspective from science (not math)&lt;/a&gt; Starting at 1:54:00 in the video. &lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Computation Time</title>
      <link>https://shaojiejiang.github.io/post/en/adaptive-computation-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Apr 2020 10:46:44 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shaojiejiang.github.io/post/en/adaptive-computation-time/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My notes for the paper: Adaptive Computation Time for Recurrent Neural Networks&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;additive-vs-multiplicative-halting-probability&#34;&gt;Additive vs multiplicative halting probability&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Multiplicative:&lt;/strong&gt; In the paper (footnote 1), the authors discuss throughly their considerations for deciding the computation time.
It is acknowledged by the authors that using the logits $h_n^t$ as the halting probability at step $n$ might be more straightforward.
Therefore, the overall halting probability is calculated as $$p_t^n = h_t^n \prod_{u=1}^{n-1} (1 - h_t^u)$$.
We use $(1 - h_t^u)$ for previous update steps to indicate that the updating is *not* stopped until $n$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As each $p_t^n \in (0, 1)$ is relatively independent with each other and $\sum p_t^n$ is not bound to 1, this approach &lt;em&gt;does not&lt;/em&gt; restrict the update depth to grow arbitrarily.
The model can be of course trained to lower the expected ponder time $\rho_t = \sum n p_t^n$, but it is observed in the experiments that the resulting model is not preferable in two ways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$h_t^1$ is usually just below threshold, intermediate $h_t^n = 0$, and final $h_t^N$ is high enough to halt the update.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;as the expectation is low, $p_t^N \ll p_t^1$, but the network learns to have a much higher magnitude of output states at step $N$, so that the final output is still dominated by the final state.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Additive:&lt;/strong&gt; In contrast, the additive approach have an constraint of $\sum p_t^n = 1$, so that the probability is decreased monotonically with the number of updates growing larger.
Though being non-differentiable, the total ponder time (total updates at all positions) is penalized to avoid consuming unnecessary computation.
There is still one drawback of this approach, however.
The performance is sensitive to the penalty factor $\tau$, which is not intuitive to choose as a hyperparameter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1603.08983&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Adaptive Computation Time for Recurrent Neural Networks&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
